{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "In one anecdote, this book’s author beheaded two women when he was asked to supervise a battle between 180 courtesans. This book postulates the following hierarchy of targets: ideas, then alliances, then armies, then cities. This book’s first chapter, about planning, lays out five fundamental factors in its title discipline including seasonal changes and terrain. Understanding battlefield geography is advocated in, for ten points, what strategy book written during the Spring and Autumn Period by Sun Tzu?",
      "answer": "The Art of War or Sunzi bingfa"
    },
    {
      "question": "Description acceptable. In the final days of this event, Operation Thunder was called off when Viktor Karpukhin believed there would be too many civilian deaths. This event’s failure led to the suicide of Boris Pugo and arrest of KGB chief Vladimir Kryuchkov. The State Committee on the State of Emergency was opposed by civilians erecting barricades outside the Russian White House during this event, where the Gang of Eight was thwarted by a speech atop a tank given by Boris Yeltsin. For ten points, name this coup that targeted the final leader of the Soviet Union.",
      "answer": [
        "August Coup or August Putsch",
        "descriptions of the 1991 coup against Mikhail Gorbachev"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This woman was represented by James Bradwell after she was involuntarily committed to Bellevue Place. This woman accused Elizabeth Keckley of violating her privacy by publishing Behind the Scenes. William Mumler took a photograph of this woman that supposedly shows the ghost of her dead husband in the background. Edwin Stanton ordered this woman to be removed from a room in the Peterson House, as she was too emotional over the shooting of her husband. For ten points, name this First Lady during the Civil War.",
      "answer": [
        "Mary Ann Todd Lincoln",
        "either",
        "both surnames"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This country is referenced as the “Island of St. Lawrence” in early maps, and it was the last stop on a route known as the “pirate round.” This island’s largest tourist site is its island of Nosy Be, and it contains a large area of karst pinnacles in its Tsingy de Bemaraha National Park. This country is the home of the Merina ethnic group, who introduced a language in the Malayo-Polynesian family to this country. For ten points, name this former French island colony off the southeast coast of Africa.",
      "answer": "Madagascar"
    },
    {
      "question": "One member of this family was the target of the unsuccessful August Faction incident to remove him from office. Another of this family’s members pursued the songun policy and violated an Agreed Framework that he had signed with Madeleine Albright. One member of this family built a cult of personality glorifying Mount Paektu and introduced the state ideology of Juche. For ten points, name this family that, for three generations, has ruled North Korea.",
      "answer": "Kim family"
    },
    {
      "question": "The Yakama peoples’ access to this industry was upheld in the Supreme Court case U.S. v. Winans. Under Grover Cleveland, the Retaliation Act and the Bayard-Chamberlain Treaty dealt with a dispute concerning this industry. Along with settling the Alabama claims, the 1871 Treaty of Washington allowed Americans access to this industry around Nova Scotia. The Grand Banks region has been a historical hotbed of, for ten points, what industry whose recreational “fly” version was popularized by Ernest Hemingway and other anglers?",
      "answer": "fishing industry"
    },
    {
      "question": "Demonstrators for this cause gained sympathy after the televised Santa Cruz massacre. After the success of this cause, Xanana Gusm˜ao [sha-na-na goos-mao] was released from prison and won an ensuing election. This cause gained international recognition after Carlos Bela and Jose Ramos-Horta won the 1996 Nobel Peace Prize for their advocacy of it. Fretilin fought for this cause, which was assisted by UN-backed Australian intervention. For ten points, name this cause that succeeded after Indonesian forces ended their 23-year occupation of a neighboring territory.",
      "answer": [
        "independence of East Timor from Indonesia or independence of the Democratic Republic of Timor-Leste",
        "equivalents, like freeing East Timor from Indonesia",
        "descriptions of ending the Indonesian occupation of East Timor before “Indonesia” is read",
        "prompt on partial answers like “freeing East Timor” without mention of Indonesia",
        "the word “independence”"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This man’s namesake company created an advertisement that played off Emanuel Leutze’s Westward the Course of Empire Takes its Way. This man sued John Henry Manny over patent infringement, but lost to a team of lawyers that included Edwin Stanton and Abraham Lincoln. This man drove rival Obed Hussey out of business by obtaining the rights to a cutter-bar mechanism. An 1837 invention of this man helped Midwest farmers harvest wheat more efficiently. For ten points, name this businessman and inventor of the mechanical reaper.",
      "answer": "Cyrus Hall McCormick"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man wrote that the U.S. “gives to bigotry no sanction, to persecution no assistance” in a letter to the Touro Synagogue in Newport. Lewis Nicola sent this man a letter advocating the styling of a monarchy; that Newburgh Letter was written a year before this man dissolved the mostly unrelated Newburgh Conspiracy. A letter claiming that this man was a “weak general” was sent to Horatio Gates by Thomas Conway, who led a “cabal” calling for this man to be replaced. For ten points, name this president who wrote many letters from his home in Mount Vernon.",
      "answer": "George Washington"
    },
    {
      "question": "The northernmost point of this structure was Limestone Corner, which was built at the site of Milecastle 30. The Vallum was a ditch found near this structure, which was built before a similar structure intended to repel the Caledonians. The River Tyne was one endpoint of this structure, which was largely made of turf and built years before a structure further north was begun by Antoninus Pius. For ten points, name this defensive structure built by the third of the Five Good Emperors in Britain.",
      "answer": "Hadrian’s Wall"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This event was investigated by Hubert Williams, who assisted in compiling the Webster Report. A photograph taken during this event shows two men with handguns taking cover behind a forklift. During this event, Reginald Denny suffered 91 skull fractures after being pulled out of his truck and beaten. In the prelude to this event, George Holliday filmed a man being attacked by Timothy Wind and Lawrence Powell. The impassioned plea “Can we all get along?” was made during, for ten points, what 1992 race riot in California?",
        "answer": [
          "1992 Los Angeles riots",
          "Rodney King riots",
          "“1992” and “riot” not needed after mentioned"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The 1992 L.A. riots were a response to the acquittal of the policemen who beat Rodney King; violence was particularly concentrated against this ethnic group, partially due to the light sentencing of a member of this ethnicity for the murder of 15-year-old Latasha Harlins.",
        "answer": "Korean-Americans"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This ruler had Stanislaw I installed in his place in the Treaty of Altranst¨adt. During one campaign, this ruler deposed Augustus the Strong after crossing the Du¨na river. This ruler had the traitor Johann Patkul broken on the wheel for engineering an alliance against this man. Despite entering into an alliance with Ivan Mazepa, this ruler was completely defeated in a 1709 Battle against Peter the Great. For ten points, name this Swedish king who lost the Great Northern War.",
        "answer": "Charles XII of Sweden"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Charles XII’s loss to Peter the Great at this 1709 battle in modern Ukraine marked the end of Sweden’s dominance in northern Europe.",
        "answer": "Battle of Poltava"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This composer wrote a set of five “canonic variations” on a Christmas hymn first published in the Wittenberg hymnal, “Von Himmel Hoch.” Picander wrote the libretto for a Good Friday work by this man based on the title Gospel. This composer advocated for a certain tuning system in a keyboard work that pairs a prelude and fugue in each key. For ten points, name this Baroque composer of the St. Matthew Passion and two books of The Well-Tempered Clavier.",
        "answer": "Johann Sebastian Bach"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In addition to “Von Himmel Hoch,” J.S. Bach wrote a cantata on the hymn “A Mighty Fortress Is Our God.” Those works were both originally written by what man?",
        "answer": "Martin Luther"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In 1933, the German Student Union carried out this action against Magnus Hirschfeld’s Institute of Sex Research. The Shi Jing and Shujing were subject to this action on the suggestion of chancellor Li Si [lee see]. According to the Records of the Grand Historian, Confucian scholars were buried alive and this action was carried out in China. In 15th century Florence, Savonarola ordered, for ten points, what destructive action to be performed on “Vanities” like Boccaccio’s Decameron?",
        "answer": [
          "book burning",
          "equivalent descriptions"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The burying of the Confucian scholars and burning of the books took place under this Chinese dynasty, as described by Sima Qian’s Records of the Grand Historian.",
        "answer": "Qin dynasty"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "During this battle, Baroness Frederika Riedesel fled to the Marshall House, where refugees endured hours of bombardment. At this battle, Ebenezer Learned commanded the ineffective 1st Canadian Regiment. Simon Fraser was killed in this battle, whose field is home to the Boot Monument, which was erected to honor Benedict Arnold’s sacrifice. The Battle of Freeman’s Farm was part of, for ten points, what 1777 victory for Horatio Gates that prompted French intervention in the American Revolution?",
        "answer": [
          "Battle of Saratoga",
          "Battle of Freeman’s Farm until mentioned"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Battle of Saratoga was an embarrassing defeat for this British officer, whose forces were allowed to return to England as long as they didn’t return later in the war.",
        "answer": "John Burgoyne"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In the last scene of this book, its narrator looks into a mirror in a hospital and sees a corpse staring back at him. This book was originally published in French with an introduction by its author’s friend Francois Mauriac. The main character of this book refuses to celebrate the New Year after watching a child slowly die in a hanging. In this book, Moshe the Beadle warns the townspeople of Sighet of a series of coming atrocities, which claim the life of the narrator’s father Chlomo. For ten points, name this Holocaust memoir by Elie Wiesel.",
        "answer": "Night or Nuit"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Like Elie Wiesel’s Night, this Italian author’s semi-autobiographical books such as If This Is a Man, The Drowned and the Saved, and The Periodic Table deal with his time in Auschwitz and other concentration camps.",
        "answer": "Primo Levi"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A member of this group was acquitted of murder by reason of self-defense in part because Baird Bryant filmed the victim pulling out a revolver. Marty Balin lost consciousness after being punched in the head by a member of this organization. An 18-year-old named Meredith Hunter was fatally stabbed by a member of this organization, which was paid $500 in beer to provide security for bands like Rolling Stones at the 1969 Altamont Free Concert in California. An Air Force squadron inspired the name of, for ten points, what outlaw motorcycle club?",
        "answer": "Hells Angels Motorcycle Club"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This band helped organize the Altamont Free Concert, but never took the stage amid the growing violence. Jerry Garcia fronted this band until his 1995 death.",
        "answer": "The Grateful Dead"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man gained power after pressing corruption charges against Charles La Vieuville, and he had earlier fallen from grace when Charles de Luynes assassinated this man’s patron, Concino Concini. Marie de Medici attempted to remove this man on the Day of the Dupes. Though this man ordered the siege of a Huguenot stronghold in 1627, he allied France with the Protestants during the Thirty Years War. For ten points, name this advisor to Louis XIII who was succeeded by Cardinal Mazarin.",
        "answer": "Cardinal Richelieu"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Richelieu ordered the siege of this Huguenot stronghold, a city of some 30,000 people on the Atlantic coast. The English sent two fleets to try to relieve this city, but neither worked.",
        "answer": "Siege of La Rochelle"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Whitewater Scandal",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "First Lady investigated for Whitewater, the wife of Bill Clinton.",
          "answer": "Hillary Rodham Clinton or HRC"
        },
        {
          "question": "State where Bill Clinton served as governor, the site of the Whitewater properties.",
          "answer": "Arkansas"
        },
        {
          "question": "Midterm election year in which the Democrats suffered amid the scandal and the Republican “Contract with America.”",
          "answer": "1994"
        },
        {
          "question": "Independent counsel assigned to investigate the Whitewater scandal.",
          "answer": "Kenneth Starr"
        },
        {
          "question": "White House intern whose relationship with President Clinton became part of the broad Whitewater investigation.",
          "answer": "Monica Lewinsky"
        },
        {
          "question": "Attorney General under Clinton who appointed Robert Fiske as special prosecutor.",
          "answer": "Janet Reno"
        },
        {
          "question": "Surname of the family with whom the Clintons purchased the Whitewater lots.",
          "answer": [
            "McDougal family",
            "Jim and/or Susan McDougal"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Deputy White House Counsel who committed suicide in 1993, sparking many conspiracy theories related to Whitewater.",
          "answer": "Vince Foster"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "The Troubles in Northern Ireland",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Capital city of Northern Ireland, where murals commemorate the Troubles.",
          "answer": "Belfast"
        },
        {
          "question": "British Prime Minister targeted by an assassination attempt at the Brighton Hotel in 1984.",
          "answer": "Margaret Thatcher"
        },
        {
          "question": "Political arm of the provisional IRA, a leftist party that abstains from its UK Parliament seats.",
          "answer": "Sinn F´ein"
        },
        {
          "question": "1998 agreement that created the Northern Ireland Assembly, named for a religious holiday.",
          "answer": "Good Friday Agreement"
        },
        {
          "question": "1972 event in which unarmed protesters were shot by the British Army in Londonderry.",
          "answer": "Bloody Sunday"
        },
        {
          "question": "Short-lived 1974 agreement that established a power-sharing Executive in Northern Ireland.",
          "answer": "Sunningdale Agreement"
        },
        {
          "question": "Man who was elected to Parliament while leading a fatal 1981 hunger strike at Maze Prison.",
          "answer": "Robert “Bobby” Sands"
        },
        {
          "question": "Presbyterian cleric famous for giving the 1986 “never never never” speech.",
          "answer": "Ian Paisley"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Genghis Khan",
      "prompt": "In this life of Genghis Khan, name the",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Modern-day country in which he was born.",
          "answer": "Mongolia"
        },
        {
          "question": "Birth name given to him which he later shed in favour of the title Genghis Khan.",
          "answer": "Temujin"
        },
        {
          "question": "Purpose served by the Yassa, which Genghis wrote. Other examples include Justinian’s Corpus Juris Civilis.",
          "answer": "law code"
        },
        {
          "question": "Son of Genghis Khan who succeeded him as Great Khan.",
          "answer": "O¨gedei Khan"
        },
        {
          "question": "Oldest surviving work in the Mongolian language; it shares its English name with a Procopius work about Justinian.",
          "answer": [
            "Secret History",
            "The Secret History of the Mongols"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Islamic Empire ruled by Ala ad-Din Muhammad that was completely destroyed by Genghis in the early 13th century.",
          "answer": "Khwarazmian Empire"
        },
        {
          "question": "First wife of Genghis Khan, who was kidnapped by the Merkits.",
          "answer": "B¨orte"
        },
        {
          "question": "Battle near a river in which Mongolian forces under Jebe and Subutai decisively defeated the Kievan Rus.",
          "answer": "Battle of the Kalka River"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Description acceptable. It is thought that one of these documents states “my name is” Alfred E. Neuman, the mascot of Mad Magazine. The final one of these documents explains a map with a compass set to magnetic north on Mount Diablo. Many (20 pts)",
        "drawings in these documents were inspired by Harvey Balls. The meaning of the first of these documents was identified quickly by the supposition that it repeatedly used the word (10 pts)",
        "“kill” and the phrase “I like killing.” These documents were signed with a cross and a circle. For ten points, name these coded messages written by a San Francisco serial killer."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "the Zodiac Killer’s letters",
        "Zodiac ciphers, Zodiac cryptograms, etc."
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) When this figure’s wife was harassed by the slime-spewing Long Eel, he cut its head off with a stone axe. This figure, who is the “skillful” member of a group of similarly named (20 pts)",
        "“forgetful” siblings, once used a stone axe to kill a giant eel. This figure uses his grandmother’s jawbone first to ensnare the sun into traveling more slowly and then to raise (10 pts)",
        "islands from the depths of the Pacific Ocean. For ten points, name this Polynesian trickster god who shares his name with the second-largest Hawaiian island."
      ],
      "answer": "Maui"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man’s father was killed at Piacenza after the Heruls and Torcilingi joined a rival who promised them land grants. A play by Friedrich Du¨rrenmatt focuses on the demise of this Roman emperor, who was overthrown by a former leader of the (20 pts)",
        "federati who went on to take over his capital. Julius Nepos disputed this man’s claim to power. This man’s father, Orestes, served (10 pts)",
        "Attila the Hun and appointed this man ruler at age 16. Odoacer overthrew, for ten points, what last emperor of the Western Roman Empire?"
      ],
      "answer": "Romulus Augustulus or Flavius Romulus Augustus"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This type of company titles a work by Picasso that includes in an illustration of a woman’s torso, Au Bon March´e [oh bon mar-shay]. One of these companies, Schlesinger and Mayer, commissioned a (20 pts)",
        "building with ornate cornices on a terracotta fac¸ade; that early skyscraper, later known as the Carson (10 pts)",
        "Pirie Scott building, was designed by Louis Sullivan and built in Chicago, where the Willis Tower was originally named for one of these companies. For ten points, name these large retail companies like Macy’s and Sears."
      ],
      "answer": "department stores"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In this battle, Corporal Mager Bradley was among 228 casualties for the 333rd Field Artillery Battalion. The Baraque Michel crossroads were the intended landing point for a paratrooper drop at this battle’s Operation (20 pts)",
        "St¨osser. During this battle, 84 American prisoners of war were killed at the Baugnez [bone-yay] crossroads by Joachim Peiper [yo-ah-keem pie-per] in the (10 pts)",
        "Malmedy Massacre. Operation Watch on the Rhine was the German name of, for ten points, what World War II battle in the Ardennes forest?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Battle of the Bulge",
        "Ardennes Counteroffensive before “Ardennes” is said",
        "Operation Watch on the Rhine",
        "Wacht am Rhein before mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Al Franken wrote a speculative account of this election year titled Why Not Me?. “The Shrub” led push-polling in South Carolina during this election year, during which David Foster Wallace reported for Rolling Stone while riding the (20 pts)",
        "Straight Talk Express. Shortly before this election, a primary-loser released his memoir Faith of My Fathers about his service as a naval aviator in the (10 pts)",
        "Vietnam War. The eventual loser in this election year went on to win a Nobel Peace Prize in part for his book An Inconvenient Truth. For ten points, name this election year in which Al Gore lost to George W. Bush."
      ],
      "answer": "U.S. Presidential Election of 2000"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Description acceptable. A rebellion against this type of legislation in Perm claimed it was invalid because it wasn’t written in gold letters. Anton Petrov led a rebellion in Bezdna because he couldn’t find the Cross of St. Anne in the document applying this type of legislation. (20 pts)",
        "Peace mediators were elected to negotiate the second phase outlined by this legislation, called “temporary obligations,” in which its subjects continued to give the (10 pts)",
        "obrok. This legislation included redemption loans to help pay for land reallocation. For ten points, name this legislation that was issued by Alexander II in 1861, ostensibly ending feudal suppression."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "abolishing serfdom in Russia",
        "equivalent descriptions"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This event was planned by Maurice Challe and Albert Gazier, who met with a Prime Minister at Chequers. During this event, Charles Keightley commanded an invasion in Operation Musketeer. The Protocol of (20 pts)",
        "S´evres was a response to this crisis, which was caused in part by a withdrawal of funding by John Foster Dulles. The failure of the (10 pts)",
        "Franco-British intervention in this crisis led to the resignation of Anthony Eden. For ten points, name this 1956 crisis in which a European-backed Israeli invasion sought to capture a namesake waterway in Egypt."
      ],
      "answer": "Suez Canal Crisis"
    }
  ]
}